	<preface>
		<title>
			Introduction
		</title>
			<para>
				&gs; parses the output files of ADF, Dalton, Firefly, GAMESS, GAMESS-UK, Gaussian, Jaguar, Molpro, NWChem, ORCA, Psi and QChem calculations to extract useful information.
			</para>
			<para>
				It is written by Noel O'Boyle and is available for free under the GNU Public License. For up-to-date information, please see <ulink url="http://gausssum.sf.net">http://gausssum.sf.net</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>
				&gs; version &version; can do the following:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>display all lines containing a certain phrase</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>follow the progress of the SCF convergence</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>follow the progress of a geometry optimisation</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>extract molecular orbital information, including contributions of groups of atoms to the molecular orbitals</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>plot the density of states spectrum (and the partial density of states, in the case of groups of atoms)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>plot the crystal orbital overlap population (COOP) spectrum, which gives information on the bonding/anti-bonding nature of an overlap between atoms/groups</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>extract information on the UV-Vis transitions, including the change in the charge density of groups of atoms</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>plot the UV-Vis spectrum and the circular dichroism spectrum</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>extract information on IR and Raman vibrations</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>plot the IR and Raman spectra, which may be scaled using general or individual scaling factors</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Handle compressed log files (.zip, .gz, .bz2) as easily as regular log files.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>


<para>Release Notes for Version 3.0.1:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Update in parsing library (to cclib 1.3.1+) adding support for several additional computational chemistry packages</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Avoid use of deprecated "oldnumeric" numpy module (Clyde Fare, Erlendur Jónsson)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Correct name of output folder to gausssum3 (Angelo Rossi)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Release Notes for Version 3.0:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>This is the first version of &gs; that uses Python 3 instead of Python 2</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Use Matplotlib instead of Gnuplot</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Update in parsing library (to cclib r1064)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

            <para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.6.1: Bugfix for 2.2.6. Gnuplot location undefined for new users of GaussSum (Guillaume Lamoureux).</para>

			<para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.6: A patch from Thomas Pijper was integrated to enable calculation of Raman intensities (from Raman activity). Support has been added for calculating charge density changes for unrestricted calculations (requested by Phil Schauer). Blank lines in Groups.txt are now ignored.</para>
			<para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.5: Parser updated to cclib r923 (Ben Stein, Marius Retegan). Removed minus signs in output for TD-DFT (previously these indicated the sign of the contribution). Corrected equation used for circular dichroism to match that from Stephens and Harada (see circular dichroism docs for ref). Thanks to Li-She Gan for identifying this problem and pointing me to this paper.</para>
			<para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.4: Parser updated to cclib r912 (Tiago Silva).</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.3: Fix serious bug with EDDM (Carlo Nervi, Carlos Silva Lopez). Parser updated to cclib r884 (Mahesh Kumar, Dan Matusek).</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.2: Fix problems with Linux version (Daniel Liedert). Minor doc fixes (Irena Efremenko).</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.1: Fix bug in importing cclib (Daniel Liedert). Parser updated to handle Gaussian09 CD output (Rino Pescitelli).</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.2.0:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Update in parsing library (to cclib r877)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Added support for creating EDDM maps with Gaussian</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Release Notes for Version 2.1.6: Can now handle unrestricted TD-DFT calculations correctly (previously there were errors in the contribution descriptions in UVData.txt).</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.1.5: Updated cclib to cclib 0.9+ (r840). Fixed problem reparsing GeoOpts. Fixed problem with exe on Windows with default Gnuplot and Docs locations.</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.1.4: Bugfixes for UVData.txt which had incorrect % contributions of singly-excited configurations and incorrect changes in electron density of groups.</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.1.3: Bugfixes for incorrect data for energies in CDSpectrum.txt and incorrect units in heading in UVData.txt. Updated cclib to cclib 0.8 beta</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.1.2: Bugfix for off-by-one error in orbital names in major and minor contributions in UVData.txt.</para>
<para>Release Notes for Version 2.1.1: Updated the code to save results to gausssum2.1 subfolder, along with some minor documentation fixes</para>

<para>Release Notes for Version 2.1.0:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Major update in parsing library (upgraded from cclib 0.6.1 to cclib 0.8dev)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Jaguar log files now supported</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Compressed log files (.zip, .gz., .bz2) supported</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Underlying code now uses Numpy for numerical calculation, rather than the deprecated Numeric</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Fixed error in the output of DOS_spectrum.txt where the 'Total' column was equal to the values for the first group</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Fixed problem plotting the COOP</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>Release Notes for Version 2.0.6: Plotting the PDOS was failing due to 'type' issues with Numeric arrays (due to changes in cclib 0.6.1).</para>

<para>Release Notes for Version 2.0.5: Parsing was failing for Gaussian files with "pop=regular".</para>

<para>Release Notes for Version 2.0.4: Plotting vibrational frequencies now works for GAMESS calculations that have imaginary frequencies (bug fix in cclib).</para>

<para>Release Notes for Version 2.0.3: Plotting vibrational frequencies now works for frequencies that don't have symmetry labels.</para>

<para>Release Notes for Version 2.0.2: COOP now works for unrestricted calculations.</para>

<para>
Release Notes for Version 2.0: main differences compared to &gs; 1.0
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>This is the first release of &gs; that uses <ulink url="http://cclib.sf.net">cclib</ulink> to parse output files.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Calculation of the DOS and COOP uses matrix algebra now, and is almost instant.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Images can now be saved as .png files.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Groups can be described in terms of atomic orbitals now (and not just atoms).</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
			
		</preface>
		<preface>
		<title>
			Citation
		</title>
			<para>If you use &gs; to obtain results for publication, please cite it as follows:</para>
			<para>N. M. O'Boyle, A. L. Tenderholt and K. M. Langner. J. Comp. Chem., 2008, 29, 839-845.</para>

		<para>Here is a list of some papers that cite &gs; from 2004 to 2009. There are many more papers since 2009 and I thank you for your continued support.</para>
		
		<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>
Ligand-Selective Photodissociation from [Ru(bpy)(4AP)4]2+: a Spectroscopic and Computational Study
Luca Salassa, Claudio Garino, Giovanni Salassa, Carlo Nervi, Roberto Gobetto, Carlo Lamberti, Diego Gianolio, Ranieri Bizzarri and Peter J. Sadler
Inorg. Chem., 2009, 48 (4), pp 1469-1481
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Localised to intraligand charge-transfer states in cyclometalated platinum complexes: an experimental and theoretical study into the influence of electron-rich pendants and modulation of excited states by ion binding
David L. Rochester, Stephanie Develay, Stanislav Zali, J. A. Gareth Williams, Dalton Trans., 2009, (10),1728-1741
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
		
Synthetic, structural, photophysical and computational studies of -conjugated bis- and tris-1,3,2-benzodiazaboroles and related bis(boryl) dithiophenes
Lothar Weber, Vanessa Werner, Mark A. Fox, Todd B. Marder, Stefanie Schwedler, Andreas Brockhinke, Hans-Georg Stammler, Beate Neumann, Dalton Trans., 2009, (8),1339-1351
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
The Chromophore Structure of the Cyanobacterial Phytochrome Cph1 As Predicted by Time-Dependent Density Functional Theory
Ricardo A. Matute and Renato Contreras, Guillermo Prez-Hernndez and Leticia Gonzlez
J. Phys. Chem. B, 2008, 112 (51), pp 16253-16256
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  	 Comparison of adsorption mechanism on colloidal silver surface of alafosfalin and its analogs
Journal of Raman Spectroscopy
Edyta Podstawka, Marcin Andrzejak, Pawelstrok Kafarski, Leonard M. Proniewicz
Volume 39, Issue 9, Date: September 2008, Pages: 1238-1249
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Computational and Spectroscopic Studies of New Rhenium(I) Complexes Containing Pyridylimidazo[1,5-a]pyridine Ligands: Charge Transfer and Dual Emission by Fine-Tuning of Excited States
Luca Salassa, Claudio Garino, Andrea Albertino, Giorgio Volpi, Carlo Nervi, Roberto Gobetto and Kenneth I. Hardcastle
Organometallics, 2008, 27 (7), pp 1427-1435
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
A Computational Study of the Ground and Excited State Structure and Absorption Spectra of Free-Base N-Confused Porphine and Free-Base N-Confused Tetraphenylporphyrin
Shubham Vyas, Christopher M. Hadad and David A. Modarelli
J. Phys. Chem. A, 2008, 112 (29), pp 6533-6549
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Determination of Absolute Configuration of Chiral Hemicage Metal Complexes Using Time-Dependent Density Functional Theory
Frederick J. Coughlin, Karl D. Oyler, Robert A. Pascal, Jr., and Stefan Bernhard
Inorg. Chem., 2008, 47 (3), pp 974-979
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Effect of an aliphatic spacer group on the adsorption mechanism of phosphonodipeptides containing N-terminal glycine on the colloidal silver surface
Journal of Raman Spectroscopy
Volume 39, Issue 10, Date: October 2008, Pages: 1396-1407
Edyta Podstawka, Pawelstrok Kafarski, Leonard M. Proniewicz
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
  	 Effect of an aliphatic spacer group on the adsorption mechanism on the colloidal silver surface of L-proline phosphonodipeptides
Journal of Raman Spectroscopy
Edyta Podstawka, Pawelstrok Kafarski, Leonard M. Proniewicz
Volume 39, Issue 12, Date: December 2008, Pages: 1726-1739
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Electronic structure and reactivity analysis for a set of Zn-chelates with substituted 8-hydroxyquinoline ligands and their application in OLED
Ricardo Vivas-Reyes, Francisco Nunez-Zarur, Emiliano Martinez
Organic Electronics, Volume 9, Issue 5, October 2008, Pages 625-634
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
A laser flash photolysis, matrix isolation, and DFT investigation of (?6-C6H5Y)Cr(CO)3 (Y = NH2, OCH3, H, CHO, or CO2CH3)
Mohammed A.H. Alamiry, Peter Brennan, Conor Long, Mary T. Pryce, Journal of Organometallic Chemistry, Volume 693, Issue 17, 15 August 2008, Pages 2907-2914
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Mechanism of Forster-type hopping of charge transfer and excitation energy transfer along blocked oligothiophenes by Si-atoms
Yong Ding, Xiangsi Wang, Fengcai Ma
Chemical Physics, Volume 348, Issues 1-3, 2 June 2008, Pages 31-38
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Mechanism of Ligand Photodissociation in Photoactivable [Ru(bpy)2L2]2+ Complexes: A Density Functional Theory Study
Luca Salassa, Claudio Garino, Giovanni Salassa, Roberto Gobetto and Carlo Nervi
J. Am. Chem. Soc., 2008, 130 (29), pp 9590-9597
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Nature of Charge Carriers in Long Doped Oligothiophenes: The Effect of Counterions
Natalia Zamoshchik, Ulrike Salzner and Michael Bendikov
J. Phys. Chem. C, 2008, 112 (22), pp 8408-8418
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Photoinduced Se?C Insertion Following Photolysis of (?5-C4H4Se)Cr(CO)3. A Picosecond and Nanosecond Time-Resolved Infrared, Matrix Isolation, and DFT Investigation
Peter Brennan, Michael W. George, Omar S. Jina, Conor Long, Jennifer McKenna, Mary T. Pryce, Xue-Zhong Sun and Khuong Q. Vuong
Organometallics, 2008, 27 (15), pp 3671-3680
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Quantum chemical studies on the potentially important imidates
Tarek M. El-Gogary
Journal of Molecular Structure: THEOCHEM, Volume 861, Issues 1-3, 30 July 2008, Pages 62-67
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Reversible Intramolecular C?C Bond Formation/Breaking and Color Switching Mediated by a N,C-Chelate in (2-ph-py)BMes2 and (5-BMes2-2-ph-py)BMes2
Ying-Li Rao, Hazem Amarne, Shu-Bin Zhao, Theresa M. McCormick, Sanela Marti, Yi Sun, Rui-Yao Wang and Suning Wang
J. Am. Chem. Soc., 2008, 130 (39), pp 12898-12900
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Ruthenium-carbonyl complexes of 1-alkyl-2-(arylazo)imidazoles: Synthesis, structure, spectra and redox properties
T.K. Mondal, S.K. Sarker, P. Raghavaiah, C. Sinha
Polyhedron, Volume 27, Issue 13, 10 September 2008, Pages 3020-3028
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Spectroscopic and theoretical studies on axial coordination of bis(pyrrol-2-ylmethyleneamine)phenyl complexes
Jia-Mei Chen, Wen-Juan Ruan, Liang Meng, Feng Gao, Zhi-Ang Zhu
Spectrochimica Acta Part A: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy, Volume 71, Issue 1, 1 November 2008, Pages 191-198
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Structural Properties of l-X-l-Met-l-Ala Phosphonate Tripeptides: A Combined FT-IR, FT-RS, and SERS Spectroscopy Studies and DFT Calculations
Edyta Podstawka, Pawe? Kafarski and Leonard M. Proniewicz
J. Phys. Chem. A, 2008, 112 (46), pp 11744-11755
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Structures and Bonding on a Colloidal Silver Surface of the Various Length Carboxyl Terminal Fragments of Bombesin
Edyta Podstawka, Yukihiro Ozaki and Leonard M. Proniewicz
Langmuir, 2008, 24 (19), pp 10807-10816
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Structure?Property Relationships of Polyselenoethers [?(CH2)ySe?]x (y = 1, 2, and 3) and Related Polyethers and Polysulfides
Yuji Sasanuma, Akinori Watanabe and Kenta Tamura
J. Phys. Chem. B, 2008, 112 (32), pp 9613-9624
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Structure, spectra and electrochemistry of ruthenium-carbonyl complexes of naphthylazoimidazole
Inorganica Chimica Acta, Volume 361, Issue 8, 2 June 2008, Pages 2431-2438
Tapan Kumar Mondal, Joydev Dinda, Jack Cheng, Tian-Huey Lu, Chittaranjan Sinha
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Structure, Stereodynamics and Absolute Configuration of the Atropisomers of Hindered Arylanthraquinones
Lodovico Lunazzi, Michele Mancinelli and Andrea Mazzanti
J. Org. Chem., 2009, 74 (3), pp 1345-1348
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Synthesis, Separation, and Circularly Polarized Luminescence Studies of Enantiomers of Iridium(III) Luminophores
Frederick J. Coughlin, Michael S. Westrol, Karl D. Oyler, Neal Byrne, Christina Kraml, Eli Zysman-Colman, Michael S. Lowry and Stefan Bernhard
Inorg. Chem., 2008, 47 (6), pp 2039-2048
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Theoretical analysis on the electronic structures and properties of PPV fused with electron-withdrawing unit: Monomer, oligomer and polymer
Yangwu Fu, Wei Shen, Ming Li
Polymer, Volume 49, Issue 10, 13 May 2008, Pages 2614-2620
</para></listitem>



<listitem><para>
Computational Study of Iron(II) Systems Containing Ligands with Nitrogen Heterocyclic Groups
R. A. Kirgan and D. P. Rillema
J. Phys. Chem. A, 2007, 111 (50), pp 13157-13162
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Electronic Spectroscopy of Nonalternant Hydrocarbons Inside Helium Nanodroplets
Ozgur Birer, Paolo Moreschini, Kevin K. Lehmann, and Giacinto Scoles
J. Phys. Chem. A, 2007, 111 (49), pp 12200-12209
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Spectroscopic and Computational Studies of a Ru(II) Terpyridine Complex:  The Importance of Weak Intermolecular Forces to Photophysical Properties
Claudio Garino, Roberto Gobetto, Carlo Nervi, Luca Salassa, Edward Rosenberg, J. B. Alexander Ross, Xi Chu, Kenneth I. Hardcastle, and Cristiana Sabatini
Inorg. Chem., 2007, 46 (21), pp 8752-8762
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Influence of the Substituted Side Group on the Molecular Structure and Electronic Properties of TPP and Related Implications on Organic Zeolites Use
Godefroid Gahungu, Bin Zhang, and Jingping Zhang
J. Phys. Chem. B, 2007, 111 (19), pp 5031-5033
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Syntheses and structures of mononuclear lutetium imido complexes with very short Lu-N bonds
Tarun K. Panda, Soren Randoll, Cristian G. Hrib, Peter G. Jones, Thomas Bannenberg, Matthias Tamm, Chem. Commun., 2007, (47),5007-5009
</para></listitem>



<listitem><para>
A DFT/TDDFT study of the structural and spectroscopic properties of Al(III) complexes with 4-nitrocatechol in acidic aqueous solution
Jean-Paul Cornard, Christine Lapouge, Jean-Claude Merlin
Chemical Physics, Volume 340, Issues 1-3, 9 November 2007, Pages 273-282
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Adsorption mechanism of physiologically active l-phenylalanine phosphonodipeptide analogues: Comparison of colloidal silver and macroscopic silver substrates
E. Podstawka, A. Kudelski, L.M. Proniewicz
Surface Science, Volume 601, Issue 21, 1 November 2007, Pages 4971-4983
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Theoretical studies on electrochemistry of p-aminophenol
Yuanzhi Song
Spectrochimica Acta Part A: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy, Volume 67, Issues 3-4, July 2007, Pages 611-618
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Intramolecular hydrogen bonding and photoinduced intramolecular proton and electron transfer in 2-(2'-hydroxyphenyl)benzothiazole
Dongjie Sun, Jinghai Fang, Guanghua Yu, Fengcai Ma
Journal of Molecular Structure: THEOCHEM, Volume 806, Issues 1-3, 31 March 2007, Pages 105-112
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Photophysical properties and computational investigations of tricarbonylrhenium(I)[2-(4-methylpyridin-2-yl)benzo[d]-X-azole]L and tricarbonylrhenium(I)[2-(benzo[d]-X-azol-2-yl)-4-methylquinoline]L derivatives (X = N-CH3, O, or S; L = Cl-, pyridine)
Andrea Albertino, Claudio Garino, Simona Ghiani, Roberto Gobetto, Carlo Nervi, Luca Salassa, Edward Rosenberg, Ayesha Sharmin, Guido Viscardi, Roberto Buscaino, Gianluca Croce, Marco Milanesio
Journal of Organometallic Chemistry, Volume 692, Issue 6, 15 February 2007, Pages 1377-1391
</para></listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
A Density Functional Theory Study of the Electronic Properties of Os(II) and Os(III) Complexes Immobilized on Au(111).
O'Boyle, N. M.; Albrecht, T.; Murgida, D. H.; Cassidy, L.; Ulstrup, J.; Vos, J. G.,
Inorg. Chem., 2007, 46, 117.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>
		Photophysical and electrochemical properties of new ortho-metalated complexes of rhodium(III) containing 2,2-dipyridylketone and 2,2-dipyridylamine. An experimental and theoretical study
		Wei Lin Su, Yu Cheng Yu, Mei Ching Tseng, Shao Pin Wang and Wen Liang Huang
Dalton Trans., 2007, 3440.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Photochemical cis-trans Isomerization of
cis-(eta6-1,2-Diphenylethene)Cr(CO)3 and the Molecular Structure of
trans-(eta6-1,2-Diphenylethene)Cr(CO)3
A. Coleman, S.M. Draper, C. Long, and M.T. Pryce
Organometallics, 2007, 26, 4128.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Density Functional Studies on the Effects of Hydrogen Bonding on the Formation of a Charge-Transfer Complex between p-Benzoquinone and 2,6-Dimethoxyphenol
Bangal, P. R.
J. Phys. Chem. A.; (Article); 2007; 111(25); 5536-5543.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Lone Pair-pi and pi-pi Interactions Play an Important Role in Proton-Coupled Electron Transfer Reactions
DiLabio, G. A.; Johnson, E. R.
J. Am. Chem. Soc.; (Article); 2007; 129(19); 6199-620
</para></listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
Intramolecular hydrogen bonding and photoinduced intramolecular proton and electron transfer in 2-(2'-hydroxyphenyl)benzothiazole.
D. Sun, J. Fang, G. Yu and F. Ma.
J. Mol. Struct. THEOCHEM, 2007, 806, 105.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
				<para>
Photophysical properties and computational investigations of tricarbonylrhenium(I)[2-(4-methylpyridin-2-yl)benzo[d]-X-azole]L and tricarbonylrhenium(I)[2-(benzo[d]-X-azol-2-yl)-4-methylquinoline]L derivatives (X = N--CH3, O, or S; L = Cl-, pyridine).
A. Albertino, C. Garino, S. Ghiani, R. Gobetto, C. Nervi, L. Salassa, E. Rosenberg, A. Sharmin, G. Viscardi, R. Buscaino, G. Croce, and M. Milanesio,
J. Organomet. Chem., 2007, 692, 1377.
</para>
</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
Electronic transitions and bonding properties in a series of five-coordinate "16-electron" complexes [Mn(CO)3(L2)]- (L2 = chelating redox-active p-donor ligand).
F. Hartl, P. Rosa, L. Ricard, P. Le Floch and S. Zalis.
Coord. Chem. Rev., 2007, 251, 557.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Theoretical studies on electrochemistry of p-aminophenol
Y. Song
Spectrochimica Acta Part A: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy, 2007, 67, 611.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
The electronic and structural properties of nonclassical bicyclic thiophene: Monomer, oligomer and polymer
W. Shen, M. Li, R. He, J. Zhang and W. Lei
Polymer, 2007, 48, 3912-3918
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Spectroscopic and computational studies on self-assembly complexes of bis(pyrrol-2- ylmethyleneamine) ligands linked by alkyl spacers with Cu(II)
W. Li, Y. Wang, L. Yang, A. Szeghalmi, Y. Ye, J. Ma, M. Luo, J.-m. Hu and W. Kiefer
J. Raman. Spectros., 2007, 38, 483-495.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
CO2 Fixation and Transformation by a Dinuclear Copper Cryptate under Acidic Conditions
J.-M. Chen, W. W., X.-L. Feng and T.-B. Lu
Chemistry - An Asian Journal, 2007, 2, 710-719.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
A DFT study of the chemisorption of methoxy on clean and low oxygen precovered Ru(0 0 0 1) surfaces
M.N.D.S. Cordeiro, A.S.S. Pinto and J.A.N.F. Gomes
Surface Science, 2007, 601, 2473-2485
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Syntheses, crystallography and spectroelectrochemical studies of ruthenium azomethine complexes
M.Z. Al-Noaimi, H. Saadeh, S.F. Haddad, M.I. El-Barghouthi, M. El-khateeb and R.J. Crutchley
Polyhedron, 2007, 26, 3675.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Field-induced conformational changes in bimetallic oligoaniline junctions
J.C. Sotelo, L. Yan, M. Wang and J.M. Seminario
Phys. Rev. A, 2007, 75, 022511 
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Density functional theoretical study of Cun, Aln (n = 4-31) and copper doped aluminum clusters: Electronic properties and reactivity with atomic oxygen
C. Lacaze-Dufaure, C. Blanc, G. Mankowski and C. Mijoule
Surface Science, 2007, 601, 1544-1553
</para>
</listitem>


<listitem>
	<para>
Electronic Structure and Excited States of Rhenium(I) Amido and Phosphido Carbonyl-Bipyridine Complexes Studied by Picosecond Time-Resolved IR Spectroscopy and DFT Calculations.
Gabrielsson, A.; Busby, M.; Matousek, P.; Towrie, M.; Hevia, E.; Cuesta, L.; Perez, J.; Zalis, S.; Vlcek, A., Jr.,
Inorg. Chem., 2006, 45, 9789.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
Spectroscopic and Computational Studies on the Coordination-Driven Self-Assembly Complexes (ZnL)2 and (NiL)2 [L= Bis(2,4-dimethyldipyrrin-3-yl)methane].
Li, W.; Wang, Y.-B.; Yang, L.-Y.; Shan, X.-F.; Cai, X.; Szeghalmi, A.; Ye, Y.; Ma, J.-S.; Luo, M.-D.; Hu, J.; Kiefer, W.,
J. Phys. Chem. B., 2006, 110, 21958.
</para>
</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
The hydrogen bond in the acetylene-2(HF) complex: A theoretical study about intramolecular and unusual PI...H interactions using DFT and AIM calculations.
B.G. Oliveira, R.C.M.U. Araujo, A.B. Carvalho, E.F. Lima, W.L.V. Silva, M.N. Ramos and A.M. Tavares,
J. Mol. Struct. THEOCHEM, 2006, 775, 39.
</para>
</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
Calculation of standard electrode potential of half reaction for benzoquinone and hydroquinone.
Y. Song, J. Xie, Y. Song, H. Shu, G. Zhao, X. Lv and W. Xie,
Spectrochimica Acta Part A: Molecular and Biomolecular Spectroscopy, 2006, 65, 333.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A theoretical quantum study on the distribution of electrophilic
and nucleophilic active sites on Ag(100) surfaces modeled as Finite Clusters.
C. H. Rios-Reyes, R. L. Camacho-Mendoza and L. H. Mendoza-Huizar,
J. Mex. Chem. Soc., 2006, 50, 19.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Computational studies of the interactions
between emeraldine and palladium atom.
B. Bialek, Surf. Sci., 2006, 600, 1679.
</para>
</listitem>
			<listitem>
		<para>
		Excited States of Nitro-Polypyridine Metal Complexes and Their Ultrafast Decay.
Time-Resolved IR Absorption, Spectroelectrochemistry, and TD-DFT Calculations of
fac-[Re(Cl)(CO)3(5-Nitro-1,10-phenanthroline)].
A. Gabrielsson, P. Matousek, M. Towrie, F. Hartl,
S. Zalis, and A. Vlcek, Jr.,
J. Phys. Chem. A, 2005, 109, 6147.

		</para>
	</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Molecular geometry, electronic structure and optical properties study of meridianal tris(8-hydroxyquinolinato)gallium(III) with ab initio and DFT methods. G. Gahungu, and J. Zhang, J. Mol. Struct. THEOCHEM, 2005, 755, 19.
</para>
</listitem>
	<listitem>
		
		<para>
		CH/N Substituted mer-Gaq3 and mer-Alq3 Derivatives: An Effective Approach for the
Tuning of Emitting Color.
G. Gahungu and J. Zhang. J. Phys. Chem. B, 2005, 109, 17762.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		
			<para>
				Ground- and excited-state electronic structure of an emissive pyrazine-bridged ruthenium(II) dinuclear complex.
W.R. Browne, N.M. O'Boyle, W. Henry, A.L. Guckian, S. Horn, T. Fett, C.M. O'Connor, M. Duati, L. De Cola, C.G. Coates, K.L. Ronayne, J.J. McGarvey, and J.G. Vos,
				J. Am. Chem. Soc., 2005, 127, 1229.
			</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
			
			<para>
			Bimetallic Clusters Pt6Au: Geometric and Electronic Structures within Density Functional
Theory
W. Quan Tian, M. Ge, F. Gu, and Y. Aoki, J. Phys. Chem. A, 2005, 109, 9860.
			</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
			
			<para>
				Ground vs. excited state interaction in ruthenium-thienyl dyads: implications for through bond interactions in multicomponent systems. W. Henry, W.R. Browne, K.L. Ronayne, N.M. O'Boyle, J.G. Vos, and J.J. McGarvey, J. Mol. Struct., 2005, 735-736, 123.
			</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
			
			<para>
			(NH3CH2CH2NH3)Ag2SnS4: a quaternary sulfide-containing chiral layers.
			
			Y. An, B. Menghe, L. Ye, M. Ji, X. Liu, and G. Ning,
			
			Inorg. Chem. Commun.,
			2005, 8, 301.
			</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
			
			<para>
			Ligand-to-Diimine/Metal-to-Diimine Charge-Transfer Excited States of [Re(NCS)(CO)3(alpha-diimine)] (alpha-diimine = 2,2'-bipyridine, di-iPr-N,N-1,4-diazabutadiene). A Spectroscopic and Computational Study.
			
			A.M. Blanco Rodriguez, A. Gabrielsson, M. Motevalli, P. Matousek, M. Towrie, J. Syebera, S. Zalis, and Antonin Vlcek, Jr., J. Phys. Chem. A, 2005, 109, 5016.
			</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
			
			<para>
			DFT and HF Studies of the Geometry, Electronic Structure, and Vibrational Spectra of
2-Nitrotetraphenylporphyrin and Zinc 2-Nitrotetraphenylporphyrin.
W. Li, Y.-B. Wang, I. Pavel, Y. Ye, Z.-P. Chen, M.-D. Luo,
J.-M. Hu, and W. Kiefer, J. Phys. Chem. A, 2004, 108, 6052.
			</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
			
			<para>
				Assessment of intercomponent interaction in phenylene bridged dinuclear ruthenium(II) and osmium(II) polypyridyl complexes.
			A.L. Guckian, M.Doering, M. Ciesielski, O. Walter, J. Hjelm, N.M. O'Boyle, W. Henry, W.R. Browne, J.J. McGarvey, and J.G. Vos, Dalton Trans., 2004, 3943.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>

		<para>
				Ab initio study of the electronic and structural properties of the crystalline polyethyleneimine polymer. G. Herlem and B. Lakard, J. Chem. Phys., 2004, 120, 9376.
			</para>
	</listitem>
</orderedlist>
			
		
		</preface>
		<preface>
		<title>
			Acknowledgments
		</title>
			<para>
				A number of people provided helpful feedback during the development of &gs;. The following names are listed in no particular order:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
			  <listitem>
					<para>shaloncai reported an error in the data written in UVData.txt.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Rudy Coquet reported an error in the data written in CDSpectrum.txt.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Fabrizia Fabrizi de Biani reported an error in the labels used in UVData.txt.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Tong Glenna reported an error in the major and minor contributions in UVData.txt.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Christos Garoufalis reported a problem parsing PC-GAMESS files with large basis sets.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Emmanuel Koukaras reported a bug in the output of DOS_spectrum.txt, as well as a problem plotting the COOP.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Xinyu Huang reported a bug plotting the PDOS.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Yafei Dai reported problems parsing Gaussian files with "pop=regular".</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Charles Bradshaw reported problems plotting the vibrational frequencies for GAMESS calculations.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Juan Sotelo-Campos pointed out that the COOP was only being calculated for alpha orbitals in unrestricted calculations.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Dr. Carlo Nervi, Torino, who found a bug in EDDM.py</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>James Hepburn, Aberdeen, who found that Hyperchem code had been neglected</para>
				</listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <para>Prof Ziyang Liu, Zhejiang University, P.R.China, who found a bug in the output of MO.py for unrestricted calculations</para>
                                </listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Fred Coughlin, Princeton, U.S., who found a couple of bugs in my code for CD spectra</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Li Daobing and Jordan Mantha who have packaged GaussSum up for Debian and Ubuntu users</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Neil Berry, Liverpool, who helped to increase &gs; support for GAMESS files</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Julien Chiron, Facult&eacute; des Sciences de Saint J&eacute;r&ocirc;me, Marseille, France helped me add support for GAMESS and is perhaps the first Mac user of GaussSum (see screenshots)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Avril Coghlan, formerly of Trinity College Dublin, Ireland, thought of the name (it rhymes with awesome!) and suggested various web page improvements</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Elmar Gerwalin, University of Kaiserslautern, Germany, who helped me enormously in getting &gs; (a) to run in Linux and (b) to work for other people's calculations</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Denis G. Golovanov, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow and his non-symmetry-containing logfile provided another challenge to GaussSum</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Guillaume Herlam, Universit&eacute; de Franche-Comt&eacute;, Besan&ccedil;on, France who requested and tested COOP diagrams</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Roma Oakes, Queens University Belfast, made many useful comments regarding the initial development, especially regarding <command>IR_Raman.py</command></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Ullrich Siehl, University of Ulm, Germany, who made a number of suggestions that lead to the creation of version 0.9.</para>
				</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				In order to create &gs;, I had to learn a few things. I found the following resources very helpful:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>O'Reilly's <ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/documentation/reference/html/docbook.html">The Definitive Guide to DocBook</ulink> came in handy when writing the documentation.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>O'Reilly's <ulink url="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/lpython/">Learning Python</ulink> was obviously a wise investment.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Fredrik Lundh's <ulink url="http://www.pythonware.com/library/tkinter/introduction/index.htm">An Introduction to Tkinter</ulink> was invaluable in creating the GUI for &gs;.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><ulink url="http://www.digitalhermit.com/linux/ray_tracing/povray/mesh/">The digital hermit</ulink>'s page helped me create the &gs; logo.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

	</preface>
